hey what's up guys my name is aurn and
welcome back to my C++ Series today
we're going to continue on our whole
object AR programming classes all of
that stuff and we're going to talk about
Constructors in C++ so what is a
Constructor a Constructor is basically a
special type of method which runs every
time we instantiate an object so I think
this is best described with an example
suppose that we want to create an entity
class let's actually dive into some code
and take a look we want to create an
entity class here which has two members
perhaps it has a float X and a float y Y
which is basically just describing the
position of the entity if I try and
create this entity and then perhaps
maybe give it a print function so that
it can output what it is into the
console I'll just print X and have a
nice little separator comma between the
two then y I'm instantiating the entity
here and then I'm going to call the
print function if I try and run this
code you can see that it will work
however I get seemingly random values
for the position of this and that is
because when we instantiated this entity
and allocated memory for it we didn't
actually initialize that memory meaning
that we got whatever was left over in
that in that memory space what we
probably want to do is actually
initialize the memory and set it to zero
or something like that so that our
position is zero by default if we don't
specify or set a position in the future
I'm going to make an in-depth video
about initialization for classes and all
of that so I'm going to keep it brief
here but another great example is if we
decide to manually print X X and Y
they're public so we can go ahead and
try and write code which prints out X
for example e dox if we try and compile
this code you can see that we get an
uninitialized local variable e used
error message so in other words this
code will not even compile because we're
trying to use memory that has not been
initialized this print function does
compile however but it doesn't work the
way that we expected to of course
because it's printing X and Y however
they are set to seemingly random values
so we've already got a need for some
kind of initialization we need a way to
to every time we construct an entity we
want to be able to set X and Y to zero
unless we've specified some value so
what you might want to do to do that is
create an innit method so I'll create a
method called init it'll just be void
and it will just take the job of setting
X and Y to zero now what I can do is
when my entity gets constructed I can
call E do
init and then if I try and print my my
values you can see that I get zero and
then when I call Print I get 0 comma 0
printing meaning that X and Y are set to
zero wonderful however this is quite a
bit of code that we've written extra
we've had to Define this init method and
every time we want to create an entity
in our code it means that we have to
actually run that init function that is
quite a lot of extra code and definitely
not clean so if only there was a way for
us to run this initialization code when
we construct an nty in Comes The
Constructor so the Constructor is a
special type of method which is
basically this it's a method that gets
called every time you construct an
object to Define it we Define it like
any other method however it does not
have a return type and its name must
match the name of the class if I want to
Constructor for entity I just type in
the name of the class which is entity I
can optionally give it parameters which
we'll talk about in a second or I can
leave it blank and then I can just give
it a body and in this case I can set X
to be zero and Y to be zero as well we
can get rid of this init method and if
we scroll down here we don't need to
call in it anymore at all if I run my
code now you can see that we get an
identical result to what we had when we
ran the init method however now we don't
need the init method it's handled for us
by The Constructor if you don't specify
Constructor you still have a Constructor
it's just something called a default
Constructor it's actually provided for
you by default however that Constructor
doesn't actually do anything it's
basically equivalent to this it does
nothing so don't think that it
initializes your variables at all in
languages such as Java primitive types
like ins or floats are automatically
initialized and set to zero that is not
the case in C++ you have to to manually
initialize all of your primitive types
otherwise they will be set to whatever
was left over in that memory so very
very important that you don't forget
about initialization again I'm going to
talk more about initialization in a
future video and different strategies
and ways to initialize memory correctly
so definitely check that out whenever I
get around to making that let's take a
look at a Constructor with parameters so
I can write as many Constructors as I
want of course provided they have
different parameters this is the same as
if I was writing methods with the same
name name however providing different
overloads for them so basically
different versions of the same method
with different parameters I'm going to
add X and Y as a parameter here and I'm
going to assign X and Y to X and Y so
basically I'm assigning my parameter to
my member variable here I now have the
option of constructing entity with
parameters so I simply write whatever my
I want my values to be such as 10 and 5
I'll get rid of this extra print and if
I run this I should of course get 10 and
five printing to the console like so
all right cool that's Constructors
pretty much covered Constructors of
course will not run if you do not
instantiate an object so if you just use
static methods from a class it won't run
we haven't talked about Heap allocation
yet we definitely will in a future video
probably really really soon but of
course when you use the new keyword and
create an object instance it will also
call The Constructor there are ways to
remove a Constructor as well if for
example you had a log class which you
only had static methods in so for
example I had my static void log here
let's let's call it something like right
instead and not be silly and I only
wanted to allow people to use my class
like so I did not want people creating
instances there's two different
strategies for sorting that out we can
either hide the Constructor by making it
private like so and you can see that I
get an error here because I cannot
access the Constructor if I don't do
something like that you can see it
obviously allows the construction of
this object because C++ supplies a
default Constructor for us however we
can tell the compiler no I don't want
that default Constructor and we can do
so by simply writing log which is our
default Constructor equals delete and if
you look over here we cannot call log
like this because the default
Constructor doesn't actually exist it's
deleted there are also special types of
Constructor such as the copy Constructor
and the move Constructor there are going
to be separate videos on each of those
cuz they're rather complicated but for
the basic use that is what a Constructor
is a special method which runs whenever
you create an instance of a class the
primary use for this is to initialize
that class make sure that you initialize
all of your memory and do any kind of
setup that you need to do whenever you
create a new object instance oh we've
got so much stuff to cover I'll see you
guys next time goodbye
[Music]